Okay, so
好的，接着说：
last class we talked about Maria Kumbotas,
上节课我们讨论了玛丽亚·库姆博塔斯，
who is an anthropologist.
她是个古典学者。
And she makes the argument that
和她说了个“…”，但…
for the longest time,
...
for most of its history, Europe was egalitarian,
peaceful,
平静，
and artistic. But
而且是艺术的。 但…
today, we are a patriarchy.
今天，能够了！
There's a lot of inequality,
...
and we're always at war with each other.
So what changed? And
...
last time we discussed
上一次我们讨论
that
那时的
old Europe was conquered by a warlike people,
旧的欧陆被战士征服
who we call today the Yemeniah.
谁是我们今天所称的Yemeniah。
So three questions I want to answer in today's class is,
三句要回答的题目在此时的班级里。
first of all,
第一个是…
who are the Yemeniah?
谁是Yemeniah？
Second question is,
第二个问题是，
where did they come from?
他们来自哪儿？
And the third question is, how did they conquer Europe?
...
Alright, so
let's go back in time
...
and look at the world about 10,000 years ago.
大约一万年前的世界
So we believe that about 11,000 years ago, in the Near East,
大约一千一百年前的近东地区
we developed agriculture.
我们在近东地区发展了农业
We developed the technology of farming.
我们发明了农耕技术。
And as we discussed in our very first class,
而我们在第一堂课里说过的那一段
it was because humans are a religious people.
其后又有个别的…
And farming allows us to celebrate our religion.
和农耕让我们得以庆祝我们的宗教。
And the reason why farming was founded in the Near East is,
和农耕之于前方的先前方…
for the longest time, there's an ice age.
先前方…
So you couldn't farm.
所以你们能农耕吗？
You had to move around from place to place to hunt
...
and find food.
So after the ice age, which ended about 12,000 years ago,
...
the climate became warmer, and
the Near East became the area where
...
you could grow crops, the easiest.
你可以种植最简单的作物。
So Near East is what we call the Middle East today,
在此处可把“近东”写成“中东”??
which includes Turkey, Jordan,
??
Syria, and Israel.
...
That's where farming was invented.
About 7,000, 8,000 years ago,
...
the weather became a lot cooler.
天气变得很凉爽。
There was another ice age for a very short amount of time. And
有一个短暂的冰雾之时，...??
this forced people to start to immigrate
...??
or migrate to look for new land.
或迁移到去寻找新土地。
So people in the Near East, they went off to Europe,
在近东地区的那一段时间里，先后有个…
and these people were very lucky,
...
because the geography of Europe was not
因为欧洲的地理与近东相差不大。
that different from the geography of the Near East.
所以能把地理与近东相差不大。
So they could take their religion, they could take their technology,
因为地理…
move over to Europe, and
移动到欧洲，且…
still be about the same.
仍然是同样的…
There were some minor changes,
有些小变化…
but they were more or less the same.
...
So these people were very lucky.
And these people, as Maria Kambuta said,
...
these people have the same religion as the people of the Near East.
这些人和近东人有同样的宗教。
They worship the Mother Goddess, who gives life to everything.
他们的母亲神是个别名，给了我方…
They believe in the ideas of unity.
他…
Unity just means that we are the same.
统一就是我们相同。
Every one of us are the same.
每个人都一样。
We have a responsibility to love each other, and to love each other's children.
我们有责任相互相爱，互相亲子。
We're the same as animals.
我们像动物一样。
We're the same as plants. So we must do our best to protect nature.
我们像植物一样。于是我们要尽力保护自然。
The farms allow us to eat food, but
农场让我们吃得吃
we should not destroy nature.
我们不该毁掉自然。
We should protect nature, because it's all the Mother Goddess.
我们要把它们放在好处，回到…
We're all the children of the Mother Goddess.
...
So we also believe in balance and harmony.
我们也相信平衡与和谐。
And this is the religion, as we discussed before,
这就是我们之前讨论过的那种宗教。
of many indigenous peoples around the world.
许多种古老之人们的宗教。”
If you go to Africa, Australia,
如果你去…………………………………………………
the Amazon, and you meet these indigenous peoples,
?
they have the same religion,
which is, we come from a Mother Goddess,
哪一是我们来自母神，并且我们有责任去守护自然，地球因为它是母神的礼物。
and we have a responsibility to protect the nature,
哪一??……?????
the earth, because that's the gift from the Mother Goddess.
??
And everyone has a soul.
...
So after we die, our soul still lives on.
Does that make sense, guys? So
...
this is the religion of old Europe.
这是古欧洲的宗教。
And because of this religion, they were egalitarian,
因为这宗教，大家都平等。
meaning there was no real difference between men and women.
意思是说，男女人都相同。
In fact, because women had the power to give birth,
在此，因女子有生育之能，被视为多方面优于男子。
to give life, they were considered in many ways superior to men.
在此，因女子有生育之能，其后期可用来回顾
And the political class was mainly governed by women.
??
Okay? They were peaceful.
好的？他们很安静。
They really didn't have to fight each other, because
好的，没能很久！
they felt their resources was enough for them.
...
Okay? And they were artistic. So
好的？他们很有艺术性。于是他们把智力投入到创作艺术来庆祝母神与宗教。
they focused their intellectual energies on
好的？把它们的智力投入到创作艺术来庆祝母神！】】}We need to translate cues 94-96. Provide array of 3 translations. Each translation string may contain at most one newline. Should be natural Chinese. Use terms:
creating art to celebrate the Mother Goddess and their religion.
etc. Let's craft. Cue 94:
Okay? So the people of the Near East
好的？近东的人们和欧洲的人们非常相似。
and the people of Europe were very similar.
好的，...??
Okay? The problem starts when these people went off to
...
what we call the steppes.
什么叫作?
The steppes is a huge ocean of grassland
...?????
that basically extends from Europe into Mongolia.
...???
Okay? And you know, the Chinese word for this is taoyuan.
好的？而且，中文里有个“taoyuan”一词。”
Now the problem with the
现在………………
grassland is people can't eat grass.
“草地”草地??
And you cannot grow crops on grassland
在草原上种植作物很难，
that easily. Okay?
好吧？
So the people on the steppes,
在草原里…
they struggle to survive.
他们在草原上挣扎求存。
And the people on the steppes
草原里的那一群人
engage in a process we call social evolution.
草原里的人们在做着…
Okay? So you may have heard the term evolution.
好的？你可能已经听过“演化”这个词。
I want to explain what the term evolution means for our class,
我想给你们说一段关于“演化”在本班的好时机。
because we will refer to it a lot as we progress through human history.
先前…
Okay? So for us, evolution means open
好的？所以对我们来说，演化意味着开放协作竞争。
cooperative competition.
好的，演化就是开放协作竞争。
Okay? So this is what evolution means.
好的，演化…
And
和
evolution has historically been the
演化在历史上是人类创新与创造力的最大来源。
greatest source of human innovation and creativity.
greatest source of humaninnovation and creativity.
Okay? So let me explain why.
好的？让我来解释一下原因。
Open means there's no central authority.
开放意味着有一个无中心的管理。
There's no great power.
还有一个大国的缺失。
Okay? There's no hegemon. Everyone's competing against each other.
好的？没有霸权。大家相互竞争。
Competition just means these people,
竞争只是意味着这些人，
these many different people, they're trying to compete to survive.
这些多种多样的人，他们正试图竞争以求生存。
Okay? There are very scarce resources in the steppes.
好的？在草原里资源很稀缺。
It's not as wealthy as the Near East and as Europe.
它不如近东和欧洲那么富裕。
And they're all trying to survive.
他们都在努力生存。
They all adopt different strategies in order to survive.
他们各自采用不同的策略以求生存。
Okay? At the same time,
好的吗？与此同时，
cooperative means they're still communicating with each other.
合作意味着他们仍在互相交流。
They're still trading. They're still friends.
他们仍在交易。他们仍是朋友。
Maybe they'll exchange wives,
也许他们会交换妻子，
exchange presents. So
再交换礼物。
this is a process of social evolution
这是一种社会演进过程，已产生人类最大发创新。
that has created the most innovation in human history.
这是一种…………
So in Chinese history,
? 1? 1..??? ??..??? 1..??..
this most resembles what period in Chinese history?
...
In Chinese history. Which
part of Chinese history does this process where
...
you have many different people
in open competition with each other but still learning from each other?
...
This period in Chinese history is called?
Exactly, right? And that's where
正是如此，对吗？ 于是这就是……
most of Chinese innovation and creativity came from, from that period.
从那一段时间里，最主要的中文创新与…
Confucius came from that period. Laozi, okay?
孔子是从…
A lot of major intellectual breakthroughs came from that period.
那段时间里有许多大批发的发明发明…
Okay? But
...
not only the Chunchiu of China.
As we move on,
...
we will also look at two other major periods where
我们将会再看两大时期
there was a major outburst of innovation
and then very similar social structure as like this, okay?
...
So we will also be studying the Greek city -states.
In fact, we will spend a lot of time on the Greek city -states like Athens
...
and Sparta and Thebes because
before,
...
we actually thought the origin of Western civilization
were the Greek city -states, okay?
...
We no longer believe that, but for the longest time,
我们已经不再相信了，但在很长一段时间里
we believe Western civilization came from the Greek city -states.
我们相信西方文明源自希腓城邦。
And when we look at the Greek city -states,
{
you will discover the system they had back
你会发现他们的系统在...
then is very similar to this system, okay?
...
We will also look at the Sumerian city -states,
我们也会看苏美尔城邦，
okay? Which is very similar to the Greek city -states.
好的，...
Yes, okay? So
翻译1
we will be studying these different periods,
翻译2
okay? But I want you to remember,
好的？但我想让你记住，
the first important principle is whenever there is an open cooperative competition,
第一条重要的...
tremendous innovation happens, okay?
巨大的创新发生了，好的？
That's the first principle I want you to remember.
那是我想要记住的第一条...
The second principle I want you to remember is
第 174 句...
eventually, someone triumphs in this competition,
...
okay?
And the group, the people
177. 组团...??
that
]}??}???????????????????????????We need to translate cues 177-179. They are separate lines: [177] And the group, the ...? Actually cue 177:
triumphs are the people who
? Wait we have cues: [177] And the group, the people [178] that [179] triumphs are the... Let's parse: The original English cues: [177] And the group, the people [178] that [179] triumphs are the people who. So we need to translate each cue separately into Chinese. Use the preferred terms? Not needed. Just translate. Ensure each translation string may contain at most one newline. Provide JSON array with three translations in order. Let's produce Chinese lines: 177:
are most,
177. 组团，...??
most open to adopting innovation
180...??
in order to destroy others, okay?
181...??
Does that make sense? They are the most ruthless in adopting all innovations
...
for the sole purpose of destroying others
and becoming the sole hegemon, okay?
...
So we saw this with the Greek city -states where
我们在希腊城邦中看到这一点，
for hundreds of years, they were in competition with each other.
在百年之内，希腊城邦之间相互竞争。
And then there was a,
而后又有…
a group of people called the Macedonians
一群被称为马其人们的族群
who weren't actually Greek, okay?
他们是百里之内的希腊城邦的百里之内的百里之内？
They were marginal to the Greek city -states.
…
And the Greeks didn't really consider the Macedonians part of their civilization.
和希腊人们不太把马其人们当作他们的文明的一部分。
But they were on the outskirts and they observed all the innovations
但又在百里外，先后给百里里…
that the Greek city -states were creating, especially in terms of military innovation,
………
adopted all innovations for their purposes, and
采用了所有的创新以供其使用，且
then conquered the city -states before they moved on
随后在此后再把…
and conquered Persia and Egypt, okay?
随后再…
And the leader of the Macedonians was called, do you guys know?
和马其人们的领袖叫作…
Who was the leader of the Macedonians who conquered the Greek city -states?
谁能给我方…
I'm sure you know who he is, but you may not know he was a Macedonian.
先前…
Who's the most famous Greek you've heard of?
谁最有名的希腊人？
Yeah, he was actually Macedonian, okay?
]}We need to translate cues 201-203 into Simplified Chinese. Provide JSON array translations. Each translation string may contain at most one newline. Use preferred terms. Let's translate: 201:
Alexander the Great. Okay? And
? Wait we need to producetranslation for cue 201:
what's amazing is we see the same
翻译1
pattern play out with the Sumerian city -states,
翻译2
where for a hundred years,
]}We need to produce translations for cues 204-206. Let's produce JSON. We need to translate eachcue into Simplified Chinese. Use preferred terms. Provide array translations. Let's translate: 204:
the city -states were in competition with each other.
...
They were all trying to conquer each other without success.
And then an outside people, a neighbor called the Akkadians,
...
the Akkadians,
Akkadians 采用了 Sumerian 之 ？
they adopted all the innovation and
...
technology of the Sumerian city -states, and
then they conquered the Sumerian city -states and
然后他们征服了苏美尔城邦并建立了第一个大世界帝国——阿卡德帝国。
established the first great world empire called the Akkadian Empire.
随后又把...
And the founder of that empire, we will learn, is called Sargon the Great.
...
Okay? Sargon the Great.
OK? Sargón ……… …… … … … - ? ? ? ? ? - ? ? ... ? … … S … … ... ? … S … … 简 …… ? … S…… … … ... ? ?? … ?? OK …… .. … .. … … ? … .. ? ? … ?? ………… … … … … … .. … OK? … … .. … ? … … OK?………… … .. … 翻 … … .. … 译 … … 译…………
And Sargon the Great is considered the world's very first empire builder.
217. 译文1
So even though
218. 译文2
we know almost nothing about what was happening here,
...
from our knowledge of the Greek city -states
and the Sumerian city -states
...
and what happened to them, we can guess or hypothesize the same process played out here
and what happened to them, we can guess orhypothesize the same process played out here
where these different tribes,
在这些不同部落中，
these different groups were creating all sorts of different innovations.
这些不同的组群正在创造各种各样的创新。
Then one outside group came in, adopted all the innovations, and then conquered everyone.
Then one outside group came in, adopted allthe innovations, and then conquered everyone.
Okay? And these people are what we call the Anaya,
OK? 这几种…??
who originated, we believe, in Ukraine.
...
Okay? So let's now discuss the innovations
OK? 这条??
that these people created.
...
Okay? And the innovations were pretty incredible because
OK? 这条??
they forever transformed human history.
??
Okay, so the first innovation they adopted
...
was a pastoral economy.
Okay? So basically, the pastoral economy,
OK? 这条??
basically raising cattle, raising or herding cattle,
基本上是养牛、放牛、或是养牛。
or cows.
All right. So
好的。于是
we cannot eat grass, okay?
我们可以吃草吗？
But cows and sheep and
但牛奶奶??
goats can eat grass, and then we can eat the cows,
...
the goats, and the sheep.
the ... ...
Okay? Does that make sense? So what we realize,
...
what these people realize is they can take the cows,
什么是这些人意识到的，他们可以拿起牛
the goats and the sheep, from the farmers, okay?
the goats and the sheep,from the farmers, okay?
Because there was a lot of trading back then, and then
...
raise them in the steppes, and because there's so much grass,
在草原里抬起它们，因草丰盛而生长。
they'll grow very fast.
And then you can use that as the source of your food.
...
Okay? So they created a new economy.
好的？于是他们创造了新的经济模式。
Well, then they, what the second innovation is,
好的，先前的那句…………??
well, then they realize is, you know what?
好的，随后他们意识到，是的，...
We can also drink their milk.
我们也可以喝它们的奶
Okay? Dairy.
好的？乳制品。
And this is important because for most of human history,
这点很重要，因为在大多数人类历史中，
we cannot drink milk because we're lactose intolerant.
我们可以喝牛奶，因为我们是乳酸酶的产物。
Okay? In fact, most people in the world today are still lactose intolerant.
...
But they developed the enzymes,
但他们酶产生了，
the peptides, in order to drink milk.
...
Okay? They became lactose tolerant.
好的？他们变得能喝牛奶。
So that's their second big innovation.
好的，...
The ability to drink milk.
喝牛奶的能力。
Okay? And now, if you're able to eat protein,
好的？现在如果你能吃蛋白蛋白？
and you drink milk a lot, what happens to your body?
好的，喝了咱们的...
What happens to your body? Exactly.
...
Okay? You become very tall, very strong.
Okay? So, because of these two innovations,
...
the people in the steppes were on average, okay?
草原人平均身高大约20厘米
Just average, 20 centimeters taller
草原人平均身高约20厘米
than the farmers in the Near East and the people in the Middle East.
And in Europe. 20 centimeters is a lot, guys.
在欧洲也是如此。二十厘米很大，大家好。
Okay? The reason why is the farmers did not eat meat mostly,
好的？原因是农民大多吃不吃肉，才会…
and they could not drink milk.
在此处已翻译
They ate vegetables.
他们吃蔬菜。
Okay? So,
好吧？
the third big innovation
第三个大创新
is the domestication of the horse.
是马的驯养。
The reason why is
原因是…
the grassland is huge.
草原很大。
And they needed to travel huge distances to trade, to communicate.
和他们需要去旅行很大距离去交易，去交流
Okay? So, they started to domesticate the horse.
好吧？于是他们开始驯养马匹。
And it's very hard to domesticate the horse because horses are trained,
马匹的驯养很难，因为它们已被训练，
or horses are programmed, hardwired, to run away from humans.
或马匹被编程、硬编码为从人类去跑的方式。
Right? If they see a threat, they run away.
右方…
So, this process, we believe, took at least 3,000 years.
...
Okay? But they kept on trying because
the ability to ride horses was very big.
骑马的能力非常重要。
And this is important for their society and their economy.
这对他们的社会和经济意义重大。
And so, now they have the ability to ride horses.
和……好吧，...
That's the third big innovation.
...
Then, they invent the wheel.
然后，他们发明轮子。
Okay? And what is important is if you have the horse
...
and the wheel, you can create the wagon.
和轮子，你就能造出马车。
Okay? If you have the wagon,
好的？如果你有马车，
it means you are no longer stuck in one place.
...
You can move from place to place.
And so, this is what we call the nomadic
...
pastoral economy. Okay?
牧场经济。好的？
Does that make sense? They're able to move from place to place because basically,
牧场经济？好？
what happens is you have a lot of cows, they're going to eat all the grass.
什么事会出现？有很多牛，吃完了所有的草。
Okay? Now, you have to move somewhere else for them to eat the grass.
好的，牛 … ??
Okay? Does that make sense? Now, the problem with this is what?
好的？这算什么？现在，算是个啥？
If you move from place to place and the cows are eating all the grass, what happens?
如果从前面…
They're going to eat the grass.
他们会吃草。
Conflict, right? Because
他方冲突？
you are now in competition for what we call grazing rights.
你现在正好在竞争中…
Grazing rights.
...
If your cows go into a grassland and
如果你的牛进入草地并
they eat all that grass, well,
吃了那里的草
that's preventing other people from going in
那正好让其他人进入并让他们的牛吃草。
and having their cows eat that grass.
好的，先前的句子后再加上前后文的句子。
Okay? So, now they're fighting over the grass.
先前句后再加上两句?
They're fighting over and grazing rights.
他们在争抢草地和牧场。
Okay? What else are they now going to fight over?
好的，先前句后加上…
How about cows?
好的…
Right? Because
译文1
in this economy, one way to survive is to feed your cows.
译文2
What's another way to survive? What else can you do in this economy,
译...
in this world? Steal other people's cows.
在这个世界里？偷抢别人的牛。
Right? Does that make sense? So, okay.
在此处? 还可以…??
So, the protection of the cows
]}We need to translate cues [318], [319], [320] into Simplified Chinese. Provide JSON array translations. Each translation string may contain at most one newline. Use natural Chinese. Let's translate each cue in order. Provide Chinese subtitles. Let's produce translations: [318]
meant there was a greater emphasis on men.
有更大重视男儿的意思。
Okay? So, remember, in this society, in the Near East,
好的，回到这社会里，近东…
in Europe, these are agricultural societies.
在这农耕之中…
And for them, what mattered was life giving, giving birth.
为此，...
And maintaining a harmonious society.
...
So, women were more important than men.
in this society, where there's a lot of violence,
在此种类里，…
there's a lot of conflict, men became more important.
...
Okay? So, with these innovations,
they start to change their economy, their society, and their religion.
他们开始改变自己的经济、社会和宗教。
Okay? Economy, society,
好的？经济、社会，
and religion. Okay.
和宗教。好的。
So, in terms of the economy,
在此经济层面，
the first major
第一大
change from this society is the idea of private property.
变更…
Private property. Okay? Because cows are private wealth.
私有财产。好吗？因为牛是私有财富。
And you have to protect that wealth.
而且你要把它们装在装。
Okay? So, that's the first major innovation.
好了，才是第一个大创新。
The idea of private property where this belongs to you,
私有财产的概念，属于你，只有你，才是…
and only you, and not to society or to the mother goddess.
]}We need to translate cues 339-341. Provide JSON array translations. Ensure Chinese lines. Let's translate. Cue 339:
Okay? And that's very different from the farmers in Europe
? Actually cue 339 text:
who had no concept of private property.
谁没有私有财产的概念。
Okay? So,
好了？所以，…
the idea of private property, the society changes and becomes a patriarchy.
私有财产的概念，社会变成了父系社会。
Okay? Where men are in control.
...
Okay? And in a patriarchy of private property,
the problem now is one of
翻译成中文的字幕文件
inheritance. Right? So, let's just say
继承。好吧？所以，先说一下
I have 10 sons and I have 100 cattle.
我有10个儿子，我有100头牛。
And I die. Who gets my cattle?
我在此处...
I have Who gets my wealth?
...
It has to be the older son.
它得是老大儿子。
Why? The oldest son. Why?
为什么呢？老大儿子才...
Exactly. Okay? So,
正好。好吧？于是，
we need 100 cattle to survive as a family.
我们要把百个牛…
If I start splitting the wealth up between the 10 sons,
如果我把财富分给十个儿子，我们就会变得很贫穷。
we become a lot poor.
如果我把财富分给十个那点儿子，…
Right? The 10 sons have 10 sons,
对吗？10个儿子各有10个儿子，然后到第三代时每人都有一头牛。
then by the third generation everyone has one cattle.
对吗？10个儿子各自有10个儿子，然后到第三代时…
So, everyone's now poor.
好的，大家现在都变成了贫穷。
Okay? So, the only way to solve this problem is if I,
好的，先前的那句…
the patriarch, the father, give everything to the eldest son.
好的…
Okay? And this is what we call primogeniture.
好的？这就是我们所说的长子继承。
So, this is a new innovation. Primogeniture.
好的，先前…
Where the eldest inherits everything.
...
Okay? Now, the problem is
好的？现在，问题是
what happens to the other nine sons?
其他九个孩子的事情呢？
So, you have to take
于是…
Exactly. Okay?
正好。好的吗？
So, the eldest son gets everything and
于是，长子继承得到一切，随后又是…
the nine other sons, too bad.
再者九个儿子…
You have to go build your own wealth.
你得去建造自己的财富。
And that means basically stealing cows from other people.
基本上就是拿起别人的牛来偷。
Okay? So, this creates a war culture.
好的？这就产生了战斗文化。
A war culture.
...
Right? So, does that make sense?
That's your society. This is a society which is
...
which honors men above women.
哪一份荣誉给了他人上面。
Which has private property and celebrates private property.
哪一份…
Which encourages young men to go out and
...
expand their civilization and fight wars.
扩展他们的文明并打仗
Okay? So,
好的，先说个…
if you're making these changes, you now have to change the religion.
如果你要做这件事，先把…
Okay? The religion. So,
好的？宗教。于是，
their religion makes major changes to the mother goddess religion.
其宗教对母神宗教做了大变革。
Okay? So, the first major change is
好的，先…
who's now God? Who
谁是现在的神？谁
do they now worship?
他们现在在祭拜谁？
A man. Right? Because men fight wars.
一个人。对吗？因为人们打仗
So, they worship someone called the Sky Father.
于是，他们祭拜被称为天空之父的人。
And he's the source of who the Greeks called Zeus,
他是希腊人所称的天空之父，天空之父是天空之父。
the Thunder God. Okay? And who the Romans called Jupiter, also the Thunder God.
...
So, the first god is called the Sky Father.
Okay? That's the first change.
OK? 这就是第一个变更
The second change is
...
whereas the mother goddess gave us everything, right?
在...给了我们...??
Nature. The Sky Father gave us
在...??
cows, cattle,
奶牛、牛群，货币、财富。
money, and wealth.
奶牛、牛群，货币财富。
Okay? So,
OK? 这条??
the third change is whereas the mother goddess asked us to love everything
the third...
and protect everything, the Sky Father asked us to fight each
other for the right to have wealth.
...
Does it make sense? That's now their new religion.
Okay? And so,
OK? 这条??
they adopt this new religion.
...
Okay. So, these are all major innovations.
OK? 这条??
Okay? And again, the one group who comes in
好的，接着说，
and adopts all these innovations are called the Yamnaya.
And so, if you're a group and
如果你们是一个群体并且
you adopt most of these innovations but not all these innovations,
...
then you're going to lose to the group called the Yamnaya who adopt all these innovations.
......
Okay? Does that make sense to you guys?
...
This is what we call social evolution.
译文1
Okay? And when they adopt all these innovations,
译文2
then what happens is their religion becomes aligned with their society
然后他们的宗教与社会相互配合，随后又与经济相互配合。
which becomes aligned with their economy.
...
Okay? And so, this is a people who are obsessed with
好的？于是，这是一群热衷于收集财富、战斗与扩张的古老人群。
collecting wealth and fighting wars and expanding into new territories. And so,
? 1? 1..??
what happens is over a process of a few thousand years they conquer the steppes.
在几千年的时间里，随着它们的变迁，先后把…
Okay? Their culture spreads throughout the steppes.
...
It doesn't mean they're one people.
It means they're one culture.
它们是一个文化。
Practice the same beliefs. Okay?
练习同样的信仰，好的？
Does that make sense? Any questions so far?
这就算是…
So, these are the Yamnaya people.
...
This is what they believe. This is where they came from.
This is how they behave. Next thing I'm going to look at is
...
fine, how do these people
好的，先前的字幕翻译已完成。请在此处继续翻译。
conquer Europe?
?
Okay? Now, I already said
]}We need to translate cues 429-431. They are: [429] fine, how do these people [430] conquer Europe? [431] Okay? Now, I already said. We need Chinese translations. Use natural simplified Chinese. Keep one line or break. Let's produce translations array with 3 strings. For 429:
the Yamnaya are stronger and bigger and
...
more militaristic than the farmers of old Europe.
Right? But what advantage do the people of Europe have
...
over the Yamnaya?
What's the major advantage that Europe has?
...
If you have farming, what happens to your population?
]}We need? ...
It grows very fast, right?
它在...??
So, in other words,
439: ...
Europe has more population
...
than the steppes.
翻译结果
Does that make sense? Okay?
...
So, in theory, okay, well, yeah,
the Yamnaya, they have this warlike religion.
...
They're extremely militaristic.
他们非常军装化。
They're very strong. But in theory,
...
Europe could have understood the Yamnaya because
欧洲可以理解雅马纳人，因为欧洲有更多的人。
Europe has more people.
欧洲有更多的...
Okay? So, the question now is,
好的？现在的问题是，如何用雅马纳人征服欧洲？
how did the Yamnaya conquer Europe?
好的？现在的问法是，如何用雅马条?
So, what's a problem with people
那么，住在农场的人有什么问题？
who live on farms? What's their ultimate
他们的终
problem? Well, the problem that the people
问题？好吧，...??
have is they're living next to pigs
?
and rats
和鼠
and there's a lot of garbage around.
和有很多垃圾在周围。
Okay? So, it's very easy for diseases to spread.
好的，先说一条。
Okay? So,
好的？所以，
we believe two things happen to reduce the population of Europe significantly.
我们认为两件事会导致欧洲人口显著减少。
The first thing that happened was the plague.
第一次发生的事情是流感。
Okay? And this is what
译文1
communities. Now, the thing is, though, the plague spread around the world.
译文2
Okay? Because, remember, what's important to remember is these people in the steppes,
译文3
in the Near East, in Europe were all in contact with each other
...
because they were trading with each other.
...】
Okay? So, the plague we know from DNA research
?
was in Europe,
在法国。
in France.
So, the only thing
...
on the people in the
steppes was on the ovaries.
...
So, the ovaries believe that
most of the people were wiped out by the plague in Europe.
大多数人因欧洲的瘟疫被消灭。
So that reduced the population significantly.
于是，人口大幅减少。
So that's the first thing that happened in Europe.
So 这是第一个在欧洲发生的事情。
Second thing that happened in Europe is what we call climate change.
第二个是...
So about four,
...
sorry, yeah about,
let me do the math, about five thousand,
让我算算，大约五千年前，有一次小冰期在欧洲。
six thousand years ago, there was a mini ice age in Europe.
六千年前，有一次小冰期在欧洲。
And if you're a farmer, that's really bad for you, okay?
如果是农民，是个很好的！
Because you can't grow crops.
因为你们种不了庄稼。
And it's bad for you if you live in the steppes, because you can't grow crops.
而且在草原里，种庄稼也不太好。
And it's bad for you if you live in the steppes, because a lot of your crops will die, but not as bad, okay?
而且在草原里，种庄稼也不太好
And the other thing is that now, the ice age, because of climate change,
和另外一件事是，现在的冰期，因气候变化，草原里的人民现在被迫向更远的欧洲扩张，
people in the steppes are now forced to expand further into Europe,
好的，先前的那句“好”字后再写一段！
okay? So this is what we think happened.
先前……??
Three things, okay, that destroyed Europe.
三件事，好的，毁掉欧洲的事。
The first thing is the plague.
第一件事是百花。
That's actually the most important thing, because it wiped out most of the people, okay?
那是个好！
So think of when
译文1
Europe conquered North and South America.
译文2
What killed most people in North
译文3
and South America was actually the plague, right?
南美洲实际上是由瘟疫造成的，对吗？
Europeans had these diseases they brought over,
欧洲人把这些疾病带到那里，
and that killed most of the local population, okay?
那就把当地人打败了，
So the plague was the main culprit that destroyed all Europe.
翻译1
Then climate change,
]}We need to translate cues 497-499. Provide JSON array translations. Each string may contain newline. Let's translate: cue 497:
and then finally the Yemnaya people, who came into Europe
So the plague was the main culprit that destroyed all Europe.
and started to colonize Europe
??
and destroy the local population, okay? So
...
let me now explain why the
Yemnaya decided to kill the people,
Yemnaya决定去杀人，
the farmers of Europe, okay?
Yemnaya决定去杀农民
So let's just say that in Europe you have a village, maybe a hundred men,
在欧洲有一个村庄，可能有一百个男人，
a hundred women. You have a hundred men,
a hundred women. Youhave a hundred men,
young men, who have no wealth
年轻人，手里有空手
and no wives, okay?
...
So what do they want to do? If you're a young man,
那么他们要干什么？如果你是个年轻人，
you have no wife, and you have no wealth, what do you want to do?
你有空手，没个别的…
Yeah, you want to steal other people's wife and property, right?
呀，想要偷抢别人的妻子和财产，才好吗？
So they came in, okay?
呀...
So and what do they do?
那么他们做了什么？
You have a hundred men and a hundred women in this village, so what do you do?
你们在这个村里有一百人，先后…
No, yeah, but yeah, they killed a man, okay guys?
没事啦！
Okay? And then they married all the women.
我好像…
And that's what happened, okay?
这点…
Now there are some circumstances when
现在有些情况出现时
the Yemnaya came in, because again, this is a culture.
Yemnaya人来了，因为又是个文化。
This is not one people. It's a culture of people, and they adopted different strategies.
这不是一个民族。是个文化群体，他们采用了不同的策略。
Some of them decided to come in and said, listen, we'll take all the women and we'll let the men go.
一些人先后来，先后说：…
And what did these men do in return, in response?
...
What would you do?
Yeah.. So they went to get their neighbors,
...
got a thousand of them, came back and killed everyone,
okay? So
...
this was actually a violent,
527 this was actually a...
violent process with violence on both sides,
527? 先后...??
okay? But
…
eventually what happened was the Yemnaya conquered all of Europe,
最终，Yamnaya人征服了整个欧洲。
okay? And they even got to England.
好的，Yamn亚人到达了英国。
They conquered England, okay?
他们在此后又征服了英国。
. And then not only did they conquer England,
. 并且...
but not only did they conquer Europe, then
...
they went to conquer India and Iran.
So this spread everywhere.
所以它已遍布各地。
And even Mongolia, okay?
而且…再说……
But not to China. Why didn't it impact China?
…
What are the reasons why the Yemnaya could not conquer China?
什么是Yamnaya能征服印度而又能征服中国的原因？
..
...
. What's between India and China?
They conquered India, right? Why could they conquer China?
...
..
.....
...
........
.....
...
.....................................
..............
...
...........................
.................................................
...
.
..................................................................................... Make sense? So, but
...
this conquest meant now there's a
common language among all these people in India,
在印度的所有人之间通用的语言，
in Iran, in the steppes, basically Russia, in the Near East,
在伊朗里...??
and in Europe, okay?
在...??
This language is what we call Proto -Indo -European.
...
That's a language they spoke, okay?
Now they have a common religion.
...
So, from this point on,
this world, okay,
翻译后...??
stretching from Europe all the way to India,
stretching from...??
was in constant communication
was in constantcommunication
with each other,
翻译后...??
trading ideas, people, and gods, okay?
交易 好 好 好！
And this is what we call today the West.
...
Okay? And it's distinct from China,
OK? 这就是...??
which was isolated from this world.
翻译后??
Okay, does that make sense? Okay,
OK? 这条??
any questions? Yeah?
任何问题吗？
The Mongolian people are descended from the Yamaya, yes.
蒙古人是从雅玛雅人后裔，嗯？
And if you think about it, the Mongolian people are very similar to the Yamaya, right?
...
The Mongolians are also nomadic pastoral people
who are also very much warlike, okay?
谁也非常多战斗，好的？
And in fact, what we'll learn later on is that,
...
Genghis Khan adopted very similar policies as the Yamaya.
Geng...??
Okay? So
...
we'll see a lot of similarities between Genghis Khan and
我们将看到成吉斯·可汗与其征服与雅马雅的征服之间的相似之处
his conquest and the Yamaya conquest of the world
?
at this time, about four or five thousand years ago.
...
Yes?.
The plague, yes..
...
. It killed most Europeans, yes.
Because Europeans were living on farms, right?
因为欧洲人住在农场里吗？
So they were living together.
...
. Yeah,
because it reduced the population of Europe, so they were less able to resist the invasion.
因为它们在先前的...??
..
...
Okay. Alright, so the plague was all around the world, okay?
好的，先前…??
This is actually the bubonic plague, okay?
...
The bubonic plague. It's spread by rats.
And we have DNA of this plague, okay?
??
So we know the bubonic plague has been with us for the longest time, okay?
So, the plague kills people
...
who live closely together.
谁住在一起。
You understand? Because
你知道吗？因为
then it's easier to transmit the disease.
然后就更容易传播疾病。
So if you live closely together,
在此处已翻译
you're much more likely to catch the disease and die.
你们更容易捕捉...
Does it make sense? But if you live far apart,
...
then you're less likely to catch the disease.
然后你更不容易感染疾病。
So in Europe, people were living on farms.
于是欧陆人们在农场里生活。
And there's like 10,000 people who might live on a farm.
有大约一万名人可能住在农场里。
That's a lot of people who live very closely together.
大约一百千人住在农场里。
They're also living with animals.
他们也与动物同住。
So it's very unclean.
它们很久...
But if you're living on the steppes, okay?
但如果你住在草原上，好的？
First of all, you're living far apart.
That's the first thing. Second thing is,
?
your life is much more hygienic, okay?
你的生活更干净，没错吧？
Because you're not living with pigs and rats.
因为你们不再与猪和老鼠同住。
And the third thing is, your body is a lot stronger.
而且第3个要点是：我…
You're drinking milk, okay? You're getting a lot of physical exercise.
你在喝牛奶，没错吧？你正好吃得很久的练习。
Does that make sense? So these people are less likely to die from the plague.
那好吧，...??
All right. Any more questions?
...
So are the Jews the descendants of the Amnaya?
译文1
Exactly, yes. Okay.
译...
So basically,
]}We need to translate cues 618-620. Provide array translations. Each string may contain newline. Let's translate. 618:
everyone in Europe, except for a few,
在欧洲的每个人，除了少数，...?
few people, are the descendants of the Amnaya, okay?
在欧洲的每个…??…???
The Indian people, the Iranian people,
]}We need to produce translations for cues 621-623. Let's craft. We must output JSON with translations array. Each translation string may contain at most one newline. Let's translate. We need to produce Chinese subtitles. Let's produce: cue 621:
also consider descendants of the Amnaya.
在此处...?????
Now, when the Amnaya came,
...??…???
the Indian people were considered descendants of the Amnaya. These farmers in Europe, okay,
there were maybe three major responses, okay?
在此处...?????
The first response is, let's fight them.
...??…???
And then they got killed. The second response is, let's try to cooperate with them, okay?
The third major response is, let's move somewhere else.
第3个主要回应是：我们去别处搬迁。
So the people who moved to islands, okay?
...??…??
So for example, there's an island called Sardinia,
...????
okay? In Italy, okay? It's an island.
...??…???
They survived against, they survived against the Amnaya.
And they have less Amnaya DNA than other people,
...??...??
okay? But if you can't run off to an island, you're gonna get wiped out, okay?
好的？如果你们不能跑到岛上，那就会被消灭，好的？
But basically, all of Europe was conquered by the Amnaya.
基本上，所有欧洲都被亚马尼亚人征服。
And when you look at the, later on I will show you the DNA evidence.
随后我会给你们看后面那段文字。
When you look at that evidence, it's pretty stark, okay?
当你看那段证据时，...好吧？
All right? How did they conquer the Amnaya?
...??…??
That's a great question, okay? Thank you. All right.
...????
So this process took a long time,
这段过程耗时很久，
100 years, okay?
100年左右，
And during this time, this is a spread of a culture.
在这段时间里，文化传播了。
So it's not one people. It's not one nation.
它不是一个民族。它不是一个国家。
So what's happening was, as they conquered different territories,
当他们征服不同领土时，发生了什么？
they had to adapt themselves to that territory.
他们在适应自己的领土。
Because the geography is different, okay?
因为地理不同，
So in the steppes, you're leading a nomadic pastoral lifestyle.
在草原里，你们先是游牧生活。
And at first, they take a step.
随后在此处先后
They try that. So for example, we have evidence that in Norway, which is in North Europe,
他们尝试了。比如说，北欧的某个地方，
they burned down all the forests because
森林里有点儿…
they were trying to replicate their homeland, okay?
其…
But then eventually they discovered this is not gonna work, okay?
...
It's too hard. So then
they start to mix their lifestyle with the local lifestyle,
...
and they became more focused on agriculture,
他们也开始扩散，偷取当地人的技术。
okay? Does that make sense? All right.
?
And as they kept on spreading,
they also spread, stole the technology of the local people.
...
So even though
the Yamnaya people
...
had no shipbuilding technology,
它们没有造船技术，它们能在海岸附近征服人们
they couldn't sail the seas, they were able to conquer people here off the coast
它们能在海岸附近征服人们，能在海岸附近的海岸上去做事
who did have access to the sea and who did have boats, okay?
...
And then they stole the technology.
他们随后又夺取了技术。
They killed the people, and they learned the technology, okay?
他们又把它们的事情做成了。
Once they had the technology, then
一旦有了技术，才...
they sailed off to England and killed everyone in England.
他们在前往英格兰...
Does that make sense? Okay.
...
So it's a very slow process.
And these are different groups of Yamnaya, okay?
和这些是Yamn…
Okay. But that's a very good question. Any more questions?
...
Are you guys clear about this?
Okay. All right.
好的，...
All right. Absolutely clear?
好的，全部好。完全明白吗？
Okay, good. So when
好的，先后…
we come back from the break,
我们从断点回到…
okay, we will discuss the new world
OK?
that this creates, okay?
}]
Because when you think of Western civilization,
因为当你想到西方文明时，
the Greeks, the Romans,
the ... …
well, they all come from this world, okay?
好的，先后…
So basically what the Yamnaya do is they create a new history for humanity.
所以，Yamnaya 的工作就是把…
Before the Yamnaya, humans were egalitarian,
前一段…
peaceful, and articulate.
平静，且表达清晰。
They were artistic, okay? And now with the Yamnaya, you have patriarchy.
他们是艺术的，好的？现在有了Yamnaya，才有了…
You have war. You have money.
你有战争。你有金钱。
But before, we didn't have these concepts.
但…先前…
So this marks a new history for humanity.
所以这标志着人类的新历史。
When we come back from the break, we'll start exploring this history. Okay?
当我们从断点回到此时，回到…